Guide to the Harvey J. Burgess Papers, 1903-1934 CTC.1989.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Harvey J. Burgess Papers
1903-1934
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Burgess, Harvey J.
CTC.1989.02
4 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
Harvey J. Burgess of Wilkinsburg, Pennsylvania had a short, but successful career in vaudeville. He performed as a comedy juggler from 1903 through 1913. This collection contains his scrapbooks, photographs, contracts, correspondence, and juggling paraphernalia.
Biography
Harvey J. Burgess was born in Wilkinsburg, Pennsylvania in 1886 and lived there until his death in 1960. He performed in vaudeville from 1903-1913. Prior to his work in vaudeville he had been employed as a grocery store clerk. Billing himself as "The Clever Tossing Kid", his act combined skilled juggling with a comedic routine. He toured extensively throughout the Pittsburgh region (see Appendix for a list of regional theatres referenced) and in neighboring states including many excursions into the Midwest. In 1913, he lost his eyesight and had to retire from the stage. His sight was eventually restored enough for him to obtain a job at the Swissvale Post Office, where he became Postmaster and worked for 27 years. In 1916, Harvey Burgess ran for Burgess of Wilkinsburg, but was unsuccessful because of his stage background.
Although Burgess's theatrical career was short-lived it appeared to have been quite successful. In addition to his full performance schedule, his act garnered rave reviews from both the press and theatre managers.
Arrangement
Series I. Juggling Paraphernalia
Series II. Scrapbooks
Series III. Correspondence
Series IV. Ephemera
Scope and Content Notes
Materials in the Burgess Collection are chiefly drawn from Harvey J. Burgess's years as a vaudeville juggler, 1903-1913. This entails juggling paraphenalia such as tin plates, pins, and Burgess's makeup box, with some makeup still intact. Also included is a sampling of H.J.B.'s business contracts, correspondence with various vaudeville booking agents and theatrical suppliers, programs (many from little-known area theatres), letterheads and other promotional materials, and two scrapbooks, one containing many signed photos of vaudeville performers. Burgess's post-vaudeville years are represented by several photos and a file of lengthy correspondence that H.J.B. maintained with U.S. Congressman Clyde Kelly concerning local postal issues.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Leroy McCleary in 1989.
Previous Citation
Harvey J. Burgess Papers, 1903-1934, CTC.1989.02, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Harvey J. Burgess Papers, 1903-1934, CTC.29, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Theater; Vaudeville -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh Region; Jugglers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Jugglers -- Pennsylvania -- Wilkinsburg; Burgess, Harvey J.; Kelly, Claude
- Juggling Paraphernalia, I.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is made up of the many diverse objects and items used in Burgess' juggling act.
  - 5 large juggling pins (Box 1)
  - 2 bottles
  - 5 rods
  - 20 balls (Box 2)
  - 1 makeup box
  - 4 knives
  - 9 enamel plates
  - 3 steel discs
  - 3 pipes
  - 1 large flag (Box 3)
  - 2 small flags
  - 1 monogrammed table drape
- Scrapbooks, II.
  Scrapbook 1 contains chiefly photos, many of which are autographed. Scrapbook 2 contains chiefly newspaper clippings.
  - Scrapbook 1, photographs. (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, chiefly clippings. NOTE: Shelved in Box 7. (Box 3, Volume 2)
- Correspondence, III.
  This series includes both business and personal letters. They are arranged alphabetically by the name of the sender. The business correspondence includes letters from booking agencies and advertisers.
  - Abrams, Morris (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Arlington, Harvey (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bert Marshall Vaudeville Circuit (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Billboard magazine (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bridge, Al (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Brydon's Imperial Vaudeville Co. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Canfield Booking Exchange (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Challis, Beverly, Challis (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Church Printing Co. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Cleveland Vaudeville Co. Inc. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Consolidated Booking Offices (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - George H. Webster Theatrical Exchange (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Gilmore, Charles P. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Great Mars, The (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Greenwood Theatrical Agency (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Griffin Vaudeville Circuit (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Gus Sun Booking Exchange (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - International Theatrical Co. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Inter-State Vaudeville Circuit (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Jenkins, Scott (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Kelly, Clyde U.S. Representative (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Kingston Booking Assoc. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Liberty Vaudeville Contracting Co. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Marcus Loew William Morris Consolidated Booking Agency (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - McLaughlin, I.C. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Milburn Booking Exchange Co. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Morganstern, C.W. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - music publishers (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Nagle, Irwin W. (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Nelson, Charles W. (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Nixon-Nirdlinger Booking Agency (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Polack Theatrical Exchange (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Princess Theatre Co. (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Puni Circuit Vaudeville Exchange (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Rea Vaudeville Circuit (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - stage supply dealers (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Toledo Booking Exchange (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Verbeck and Farrell (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Western Reserve Vaudeville Manager's Assoc. (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Western Vaudeville Manager's Assoc. (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - White Rats of America (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Williams, B.J. (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Unidentified (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Ephemera, IV.
  Included in this series are business materials, newspaper and magazine clippings, photographic materials, and programs for shows in which Burgess performed.
  - Contracts, 1908-1912 (Box 4, Folder 44-48)
  - List book of Theatrical Managers, Booking Agents, Lyceum Bureaus and Amusement Artists, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Programs (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Promotional materials (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Short Story, A Juggler's Arabian Trick, Harvey J. Burgess, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Collection of postcards, circa, 1906-1917 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Copper lithographic plates of H.J.B. photos (4) (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - Glass negative (1) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Oversized newspaper clippings (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Burlesque magazine, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - The New York Clipper, theatrical journal, 8/22/1908 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Billboard magazine, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Harvey Burgess' political signs (Box 7, Folder 5)